Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
You can all stay outside. I'll look after My Lady from here.
Yes.
You can speak now.
My Lady, you aren't going to trust her again
after just a few smarmy words, are you?
Why shouldn't I trust her?
I saw clearly just now...
In her sachet there was ...
If you know what was in her sachet,
then you should know what she's putting herself through.
What she said today wasn't necessarily all lies.
There could be some truth in it.
Jinxi.
Your Highness.
You've asked Su Peisheng.
What did he say?
He said that although Concubine Délice and Concubine An
are both following the empress,
things between them are not as harmonious as they seem.
Recently, the empress has been favoring Concubine Délice,
so naturally, Concubine An is feeling downhearted.
Concubine Délice is shallower and brasher.
If I were the empress,
I would consider Concubine Délice easier to control.
An Lingrong has an insidious nature and deep guile,
just like the empress herself.
It seems even the empress can't fully control her.
It's delightful to see these "snakes and rats"
at each others' throats.
My Lady, are you going to do anything?
An Lingrong made the effort to speak to me,
I might as well accept what she said.
Jade,
tell Violet to inform Lady Joie of An's words.
Yes.
Your Highness, we should start preparing
for His Majesty's visit tonight.
What is there to prepare?
I just heard from Xiao-Yunzi that the princess is still
not comfortable around Your Highness.
It's no wonder that Your Highness is still angry at His Majesty.
"Terracotta warriors are molded from a ruler's vanity,
but the sculptors have their own thoughts."
Your Majesty, have some lotus seed soup.
It can cool the Summer Heat.
Have you sent someone to see Consort Lumière？
Is she better?
Still the same -
dispirited and unhappy.
Your Majesty, even if Consort Lumière is holding up,
it still might affect the heir in her belly.
I'm also worried.
How about arranging some performers to cheer her up?
Your Majesty, performers might not reach Her Highness's heart.
Her Highness might not cheer up.
What's your idea then?
Her Highness is alone in the palace,
so she must miss her family.
But the princess is yet to warm up to her...
Why not let her see her other family members?
Her Highness might feel eased after
talking to them heart to heart.
I've thought about it.
Zhen Yuandao is still sick.
He might pass the pathogenic qi to Consort Lumière.
I'll let them reunite after Zhen Yuandao recovers.
His Majesty the Emperor!
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Are you feeling better today?
I thank Your Majesty for your grace.
I heard from Mr. Su
that Your Majesty will permit me to see my father when he recovers.
My heart is greatly relieved.
Now, my only wish is for
the peace and good health of my family,
and giving birth to a new prince for Your Majesty.
Your Highness's family is His Majesty's family.
How could His Majesty not care about them?
Your Highness need not worry.
Your Majesty, Attendant Services came to ask
if you will select a name tag for tonight.
No, I will stay here tonight.
Yes.
Did Your Majesty forget what the doctor said?
It's nice to just stay with you.
I don't want Your Majesty to endure the poor hospitality here.
Your Majesty should go ruffle someone else's feathers.
Then...
The Hall of Spring Joy.
Aye.
I'll go to notify Lady Paix.
It's just that we'll have to hear Concubine Délice whining again
when we pass the Palace of Gathering Excellence.
Why? Do they often talk about me favoring Lady Paix?
No, not often.
I've only heard that sort of talk a couple of times.
Her Majesty the Empress Dowager dislikes Lady Paix.
It's only natural for others to share her feelings.
Her Majesty is the Empress Dowager,
but who is Concubine Délice?
Concubine Délice is just jealous.
Getting angry on such a hot day
might harm Your Majesty's health.
Your Majesty,
the Palace of Gathering Excellence reported that
Concubine Délice is feeling unwell.
Will Your Majesty go to see her?
She should call for a doctor if she's sick.
I can't cure her.
Don't stand there gawking. Tell her I'm busy.
Aye.
I didn't know that Your Majesty had a penchant for deception.
I'm tired of her endless chatter.
Your Majesty doesn't need to see her if it displeases you.
But justifying it to me
makes it seem like I am the reason you're not seeing her.
Of course it's because of you.
If you were a bit stupider,
uglier,
and less good-natured and sensible,
then I might be able to put up with her.
One can have affection for both the
newly favored and the long-beloved.
Why is your heart one-sided?
It's true that Concubine Délice is willful by nature,
but she wouldn't claim to be sick just for attention.
Perhaps Your Majesty should go and visit her?
I will accompany Your Majesty;
a light walk aids digestion.
Who said His Majesty won't come to see me?
It's all because of you lot of bitches
currying favor with the Palace of Eternal Longevity
to undermine my status!
- How dare you! His Majesty is here.
- Careful, Your Majesty.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Didn't you say you were sick?
You seem better than ever to me.
I thank Your Majesty.
I was just disciplining the servants.
I truly am sick ....
Then why are you beating your maids instead of resting?
What did she do to deserve a beating?
I am her master and she defied me!
I got infuriated and hit her.
Tell me what happened.
Concubine Délice was beating my maid Violet.
She sent someone to request that Your Majesty visit
but Your Majesty couldn't come.
So she took it out on Violet.
Violet.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Was it you who went to the Hall
of Mental Cultivation to find me?
Your Majesty,
it was not me,
but Her Highness's maid Jingtai.
She wasn't the one who came to request me,
why did you take it out on her?
Because -
Because Violet used to serve Consort Lumière.
Concubine Délice has been holding a grudge
ever since Consort Lumière got pregnant.
So she often vents her anger on Violet.
How dare you slander me!
Raise your head.
Indeed, you were a servant of Consort Lumière.
No wonder you blamed the Palace of Eternal Longevity.
I would not dare.
Beating an innocent maid - you have no human compassion.
You envy Consort Lumière's pregnancy,
an offense against your superior.
And because I did not come,
you lashed out at others
out of resentment towards me.
Your Majesty, please forgive me!
Your Majesty, allow me to show you this.
Concubine Délice punishes Violet whenever she is displeased.
Look at her wounds.
Not even an inch on her has been spared!
I have been powerless to save her.
Concubine Délice constantly uses her rank to oppress me.
I cannot even protect my own maid.
Her rank?
Does she even deserve to be the head of a palace?
Gūwalgiya has no respect for her superior.
She is to be demoted to Noble Lady.
Your Majesty!
She is to move to the Pavilion of Twining Reeds
and will reflect on herself in confinement.
She shall not leave the pavilion without my decree.
Lady Joie will be in charge of the Palace of Gathering Excellence.
I thank your Majesty.
Your Majesty, no! Please!
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Rise.
I thank your Majesty.
Quickly.
Your Majesty looks better today.
The bitter medicine I drink every day
makes my face red.
The blush it gives me makes me seem healthier than I really am.
It's deceptive.
Emperor, look at how well-mannered Consort Lumière is.
I've told her many times that she's exempt
from bowing because she's pregnant.
But she never listens.
Consort Lumière's filial piety for you
is equal to my own.
It's quite difficult for you to walk about while pregnant.
Why did you come out?
Consort Lumière's belly at five months
seems to be larger than other concubines'.
The imperial doctors say I'm pregnant with twins.
That's why my belly is especially big.
Huan Huan, truly?
That's what Dr. Wen said.
I wouldn't say it otherwise.
Given Dr. Wen's skills, it must be true.
This is splendid news,
I should announce it to all under Heaven.
I am already blessed to serve by Your Majesty's side,
I dare not bear the honor of such an announcement
on account of my pregnancy.
Consort Lumière is very sensible.
I've just returned to the palace,
and I would not want to cause any disturbance.
I wish to carry the pregnancy in peace,
without visitors bringing their good wishes.
So, as for my pregnancy with twins,
until the "melon is ripe for picking",
I hope it can be kept among us.
If the harem were to learn of this, it would not be conducive to
a peaceful environment for Consort Lumière.
There's no need to reveal the news now,
they will all know when she gives birth.
Imperial Mother, I have no objection to
what you and Consort Lumière suggest.
Only...
It is a shame that we cannot celebrate
such a joyous event with others.
If the Imperial Doctor is right,
then there will be plenty of time to
celebrate with Your Majesty afterwards.
Consort Lumière is right.
Since Consort Lumière is pregnant with twins now,
it will be inconvenient for her to serve the Emperor.
Among the concubines close with Consort Lumière,
there are many virtuous and gentle ones.
I suggest you let Consort Lumière rest well
and allow the others to serve you.
If you ask me,
I'd recommend Consort Vertu for her decorum and filial devotion.
I obey your advice, Imperial Mother.
Regarding the Empress's illness,
although it's not severe, it still has not been cured.
Why not consult the Astrological Office
to see if there is a reason?
And have Baohua Hall pray for her recovery.
Yes.
Your Majesty, the Deputy Astrological Official is here.
I bow in respect before Your Majesty.
Why are you here? Where is the Head Official?
The Head Official is sick and unable to come,
so he sent me on his behalf.
That's fine.
I called you here today
to ask about the previous event of
"Roof mansion impinging on the Moon"
In the past few months,
has there been any change in the Heavens?
The Rooftop mansion impinged on the moon several months ago.
Since then, the signs of Heaven have changed
with the alternating Sun and Moon.
The Roof mansion glows faintly purple,
which emanates harmonious qi.
Portents of aggression have now passed.
Really?
Then why are the Empress and the Empress Dowager still sick?
And why didn’t the Head Official
report this to me sooner?
Your Majesty may have heard the saying:
"Positions are defined by their duties."
But I have seen that,
newly invented duties can bolster a position.
Your Majesty counts on the Astrological Office
when there are inauspicious signs.
The Head Official is therefore granted both authority
and ... a stipend.
If the astronomical phenomena were always peaceful,
Your Majesty would not need to rely on the Astrological Office.
You seem to know a lot about the corrupt ways to be an official.
I know them well, but I don’t agree with them.
There's something, I don't know whether I should say it.
Say it.
The ill omen for the Empress Dowager has abated.
But I observed something at night.
Of the seven stars of the Vermilion Bird,
the Well and the Ghost mansions have slightly darkened.
These are two inauspicious stars.
They are the lords of terror, and will frustrate one's wishes.
The Vermilion Bird commands the south,
as a guardian of the Imperial Garden.
If I may ask,
Does any concubine have a parent
surnamed with a 木 [wood] radical?
This concubine would have experienced a misfortune recently.
There are a lot of palaces to the south...
of the Imperial Garden.
The Palace of Prolonging Happiness,
the Palace of Great Benevolence,
the Palace of Longevity...
They are all there.
Regarding a parent's surname with the 木 radical...
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
As far as I know,
Concubine An’s mother is surnamed 林 [forest].
I'll check on the other concubines to be sure.
It's all right. Just tell me what to do.
It is not a serious matter.
But, the constellation is unfavorable
and may give rise to inauspicious events.
It's best for the concubine to avoid seeing others.
Just not seeing others is enough?
During Her Majesty the Empress's prolonged illness,
I heard that
Concubine An has always served by Her Majesty's side.
Her Majesty's yin is depleted from the illness.
Now Concubine An is associated with an inauspicious sign.
It might have worsened Her Majesty's condition.
Concubine An has been serving the Empress the most.
So...
Inform Concubine An that
she is not to enter the Empress’s palace again,
and that she should stay in her palace for a few days.
Yes.
Since the Head Official is ill,
why don't you
take over his post?
But I still don’t know your name.
My name is Ji Weisheng, Your Majesty.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Follow us to get updates on the translation progress.
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Peace to Your Highnesses.
Mr. Su.
Your Highness, His Majesty is staying
in the Palace of Pearl Jade tonight.
Really?
His Majesty was going to see Lady Fuca
but he had a change of heart when he got to the door
and said he would go to the Palace of Pearl Jade.
Indeed.
His Majesty is having dinner and chatting
with Concubine Vertu now.
It is rare for His Majesty to visit the Palace of Pearl Jade,
but it's even rarer that Meizhuang is willing to have him.
Before His Majesty's arrival,
the Empress Dowager had a long conversation
with Her Highness Concubine Vertu.
It is difficult to survive in the Palace without His Majesty's favor.
Perhaps the Empress Dowager opened up Concubine Vertu's mind.
Why does Your Majesty look at me like that?
It's been a long time since I looked at you carefully.
You look different from when you first entered the Palace.
One's appearance changes with the passing of time.
I have always thought of you as generous and gentle.
After all that has happened,
I have realized that you also have your pride.
I know that
these past years, you've been upset with me.
Your Majesty, I would not dare.
You say that you wouldn't dare,
but let me ask you this:
After Consort Lumière left,
the reason that you moved here
was to avoid me, wasn't it?
All these years,
I know you've been aggrieved.
But as the Emperor,
I had to consider the big picture even if it made you aggrieved.
Sometimes, I even have to make myself aggrieved.
Your Majesty is the Emperor,
I would not dare to feel aggrieved.
Your Majesty has difficulties of your own.
Luckily, Huan'er is back.
I...
Every word I've spoken tonight comes from
the bottom of my heart.
For years, you were cold towards me and I neglected you.
Now I think about it,
if it wasn't for what Consort Fleur did,
perhaps I would treat you ...
as I treat Consort Lumière now.
Your Majesty, the Emperor is finally staying at
Concubine Vertu's palace tonight.
Concubine Vertu is a sensible girl.
The Emperor has treated her coldly.
Bring them some wine that can warm their emotions
and tell them it's a gift from me.
Yes.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Peace to Concubine Vertu.
What brings you here, Madam Bamboo?
The Empress Dowager was pleased to hear
that Your Majesty is with Concubine Vertu.
So she asked me to bring some wine here as a gift.
Imperial Mother...
thought about sending over some wine this late at night.
What kind of wine?
Your Majesty and Concubine Vertu
are enjoying your time and mutual affection.
Naturally, this wine is to help the
"flowers bloom under a waxing moon".
I am grateful for Imperial Mother's thoughtfulness.
Allow me to take my leave.
If there was really mutual attraction,
there would be no need for this wine.
We still have many days ahead of us.
When you come around,
I will come and visit you again.
Back to the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
His Majesty returns.
Your Majesty... take my arm.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
You may all leave now.
My Lady, you drank so much...
It doesn't matter, just leave.
Yes.
To a heart that has died,
what's the point of words from the bottom of his heart?
Your Majesty,
it was Consort Fleur who set me up,
but it was your actions
that devastated my heart.
Even ...
Even the Empress Dowager knew
that only this wine
could grant us fulfillment tonight.
Her Majesty was certain
that after this wine, I would serve you.
What about my own affection?
What am I to you?
Does he even know...
my feelings?
Even if he knew,
he wouldn't truly care for me in his heart.
Wen Shichu...
Shichu...
My Lady, were you calling me?
Wen Shichu...
My Lady, you're drunk.
Please don't drink so much.
What's the point of being sober and restrained all the time?
Can't I just get drunk for once?
Wen Shichu...
I will send for Dr. Wen immediately, My Lady,
to sober you up.
What's the point of being sober and clear-headed all day?
Can't I get drunk just once?
Orange peel: three maces;
Ejiao: one mace;
Master, it's so late.
You're still picking herbs for Consort Lumière.
This is not for Consort Lumière.
It's for Concubine Vertu who suffers from
a poor appetite in the summer heat.
I'm prescribing some herbs to boost her appetite.
You wrote them all down?
Yes.
Wei Lin,
you're skilled enough to be a doctor independently,
yet I'm still making you do these trivial things.
It's because you're meticulous.
I know I can rely on you.
Dr. Wen,
Madam Lunar is asking you to visit the Palace of Pearl Jade.
Concubine Vertu drank too much.
Please send herbs to sober up Her Highness.
I'll go right away.
Master, you're in a hurry.
I'll write the notes that
you have left for her Palace.
All right, I'll be back within two hours.
Dr. Wen, um...
Lunar,
please go and brew these herbs.
Yes.
Your Highness,
Your Highness...
How come you got so drunk?
You're here.
I usually don't drink.
Seeing me drunk
must have startled you.
Getting drunk is bad for your health.
Why did Your Highness do this to yourself?
Your Highness...
Don't I have my own name?
Or in your eyes,
am I just "Her Highness"?
Just like any other woman in the harem?
Spending all day crying over the Emperor's frown,
and laughing for the Emperor's smile.
Your Highness, I...
Please don't say that...
Have a seat.
Yes.
I have some good wine.
You should try some.
Your Highness, I would not dare.
I have given Lunar the herbs to treat intoxication.
Other matters await me in the Imperial Infirmary.
Forgive me, it's not convenient for me to stay here this late.
So it turns out...
I don't even have someone to drink and chat with.
Your Highness...
I...
I obey your order.
Everyone says you get happy when you drink,
but I still feel so lonely.
In the palace, the Emperor doesn't act like an emperor,
and the concubines don't act like concubines.
Except for Huan'er,
I'm always alone with myself.
Your Highness...
Please don't be like this.
I know Your Highness feels sad.
Please tell me what's on your mind.
I am listening.
This wine is so good...
My body feels so warm now...
Since my body is warm, my heart doesn't feel so cold anymore.
Your Highness, wine can warm,
but also harm your body.
It's not worth harming yourself
for a moment of relief.
Aren't you and I the same?
To protect those we care about,
we will hurt ourselves.
Are we... not the same?
We are kindred spirits, Your Highness.
Kindred spirits...
Your Highness! Your Highness...
What's the matter?
Your Highness...
Stop, stop...
My Lady, the rain is getting heavier.
Shall we go inside for shelter?
The road is slippery.
It would be better to avoid slipping.
All right, help me get down.
Lower the sedan.
The "coupling joy" flowers are blooming beautifully.
Beautiful as they are,
they still all wither in the pouring rain.
Your Highness, let's go further in.
It's cold and wet here.
Who is that?
Tell her to come inside.
I'll go take a look.
Oh! Noble Lady Paix.
Her Highness asks you to take shelter over there.
Come inside.
Your Highness, it's Noble Lady Paix.
Grace to Consort Lumière.
You're covered with raindrops.
Jinxi, put a cloak on her.
My Lady, this will keep you warm.
Noble Lady Paix is fond of the "coupling joy" flowers.
Why not ask servants to put
some cloths under the trees?
Then when the rain stops, you can collect the fallen petals.
So you don't need to go out in the rain.
I thank Your Highness.
It's just that it's nearly autumn.
There won't be many "coupling joy" flowers left.
These are the most beautiful "coupling joy"
in the whole imperial garden.
These are the most beautiful ones?
The ones at the Hall of Converging Light
are the best under Heaven.
In early summer, it's like a sea of flowers.
You can smell the fragrance from so far away.
I've never seen it...
I come from a humble background,
lowlier even than a maid.
That's why I could go anywhere I wanted.
Others can gossip however they want.
Don't think less of yourself because of them.
Speaking of being humble,
I'm the daughter of a convicted official.
The rain is about to stop.
Lady Paix, how is it you're out here without a servant?
When the rain stops,
shall I have someone escort you back?
No concubines have been willing to set foot in the Hall of Spring Joy.
Would Your Highness be willing to grace such a humble place?
Am I welcome?
Peace to Your Highness.
Please sit, Your Highness.
My Lady, your cat is so well behaved.
What's so special about this big clumsy cat?
Where's Velvet Ball?
This cat is very docile and quiet.
It also has a special aura.
She rarely meows.
but when she does,
all the cats are drawn to her from miles away.
Your Highness is afraid of cats?
No.
I'm just curious
how did you tame such a magical animal?
Before I was a horse trainer,
I was a wild animal tamer.
I'm more than capable of taming a cat.
Your Highness, it's time for your medicine.
It's not good to take it cold.
I need to go back and take my medicine.
I'm afraid I cannot stay longer.
You were soaking in the rain earlier,
you should drink some hot ginger soup.
I bid Your Highness goodbye.
Put the "coupling joy" flowers away carefully.
Yes.
I was scared to death.
Such a big cat.
It reminded me of that night on Peak Lingyun.
That was so scary.
Is Your Highness all right?
It's fine. She just keeps them as pets.
How is it?
My kitchen just made these pea flour cakes.
I find them quite refreshing.
Every season has its delicacies.
It's nothing new.
Did Your Majesty go to the Palace of Pearl Jade
the other day to find something "new"?
Are you jealous?
I'm happy.
It's not that I crave novelty.
I haven't visted Concubine Vertu much these past years.
I feel I've been unfair to her.
And Imperial Mother always urges me to see her.
So I thought it was about time.
But it turns out
she still has "a knot in her heart."
So I left.
Your Majesty rarely visits yet ended up leaving early.
You need to make it up to Meizhuang.
I wanted to.
But when I went to see her today,
she said she caught a cold and could not see me.
I was shown out.
In that case,
Your Majesty should go to the Palace
of Prolonging Happiness and see Lingrong.
I don't know why, but every time
I went there, it was as though my soul was captured
and I wouldn't want to leave.
Now that I haven't visited her for quite some time,
I don't often think about her.
Lingrong has her merits.
The Astrological Office said that Concubine An is inauspicious.
I don't care much about that,
but it still cast a shadow in my heart.
I'll wait a while before I visit her again.
By the way,
I'm here today because I have something to tell you.
What is it?
People in the palace are now so vicious.
It's more than I can bear.
What has made Your Highness so angry?
If I told you, you'd be angry too.
The things I hear are probably
a thousand times uglier than what Your Majesty hears.
If I am not angered, then Your Majesty certainly needn't be.
I am worried that you might feel aggrieved.
Since Your Majesty understands my reasons
for feeling aggrieved, I no longer feel such ways.
If what Your Majesty refers to is unbearable to the ear,
there's no need to let it enter your ears,
much less your heart.
Huan Huan, I had always thought you were just gentle,
now I also see your composure and tolerance.
“Where there are mouths, there is gossip."
If I followed every little bit of hearsay,
I'd have a "string of beads in my hands."
I entreat Your Majesty:
whatever you hear, whoever it's from,
please don't be angry.
Please don't punish the harem for it.
All right.
It's the fifteenth today,
Your Majesty will have dinner with the Empress.
Don't make Her Majesty wait for you for too long.
These are some new dishes from my kitchen.
Taste some, Your Majesty.
It's good.
As good as Consort Lumière's kitchen.
Consort Lumière is pregnant.
It's only natural that she has to be more refined in her diet.
It's hard work when she's carrying a baby.
So she has a decreased appetite.
If the food wasn't exquisitely made, she would eat even less.
Everyone in the palace says,
Consort Lumière's baby is not like others.
Her belly is bigger than normal.
When it comes to imperial heirs,
it doesn't hurt to think prudently...
Where did that come from?
Although I've been unwell,
I still hear the endless gossip.
You pay attention to every concern.
But gossip in the palace
never stops, just like the winds.
If you waste energy over such baseless rumors,
it'll only end up damaging your health.
You've never fully recovered.
Consort Honnête and Consort Estime
have been looking after the palace affairs for you.
They don't take such ridiculous gossip seriously,
so why should you?
All right, I'm full.
Where is Your Majesty going so late at night?
Back to the Hall of Mental Cultivation
to review some memorandums.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.